<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: JavaScript | Andrew Adams]]></title>
  <link href="http://andrewada.ms/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://andrewada.ms/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-07T22:17:11-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://andrewada.ms/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Adams]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Popularity of JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://andrewada.ms/blog/2014/popularity-of-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-11T18:51:07-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://andrewada.ms/blog/2014/popularity-of-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week, I have been tasked with summarizing the popularity of JavaScript in web development. That&rsquo;s a tall order for someone who has never actually implemented JavaScript in a project, and whose experience with the language extends barely beyond <code>alert("Hello world!");</code> but I&rsquo;ll give it a shot.</p>

<p>JavaScript was designed to add interactivity to web pages. As a result, it is lightweight and fast. It is also fairly easy to implement and learn. It is supported in every major browser, meaning you can be sure that your scripts will run properly for almost all of your users (well, those who have JavaScript enabled anyway). There is also a large community with fantastic support, and a huge number of libraries available to use. Finally, Javascript has evolved to be used in multiple contexts from server-side to client-side. It&rsquo;s versatility allows programmers to use the same language to accomplish a variety of tasks.</p>

<p>In the past week, I have found learning JavaScript to be fairly straightforward. I&rsquo;m looking forward to learning more about using it in a front-end vs. back-end setting, but I guess that will have to wait until I get to Chicago!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
