<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: DBC | Andrew Adams]]></title>
  <link href="http://andrewada.ms/blog/categories/dbc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://andrewada.ms/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-29T22:38:36-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://andrewada.ms/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Andrew Adams]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DBC Phase 0: Week 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://andrewada.ms/blog/2014/first-week-of-dbc/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-29T22:03:07-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://andrewada.ms/blog/2014/first-week-of-dbc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just a few days ago, I completed my first week of Phase 0 in preparation for attending Dev Bootcamp. I would have written this blog post sooner, but to be honest, I needed a break from writing. I&rsquo;ve never believed writing to be one of my strong suits, but I created this blog so I could gain experience, and also improve my abilities to communicate my thoughts and feelings. As it turns out, the challenges for Phase 0 in DBC are requiring me to do just that! For every coding objective I complete, I have been spending just as much time (if not more) reflecting on what I learned/how I felt. It&rsquo;s a requirement, and I&rsquo;ll admit, it&rsquo;s a bit tedious. I&rsquo;ve been finding myself completing an objective in a timely manner, and immediately wasting an hour or two browsing Reddit to avoid writing the reflection. <em>But.</em> I can already tell that these reflections are going to make the difference between completing an objective, and actually <em>learning</em> an objective.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>When I first began learning web development on my own, I was a sponge, absorbing any new piece of information that I could find. As I progressed, however, I began to feel a bit overwhelmed by the enormous amount of resources, documentation, and tutorials available online. It became difficult to differentiate between what was useful and what was superfluous. This was part of the reason I enrolled in DBC; I needed some guidance and direction from those who truly know the difference. Part of the issue, though, was that the more I read, the more I started to skim and skip through sections of material. The satisfaction of completing a chapter in a book became irrelevant when I realized that I didn&rsquo;t understand most of it. But this past week, when I was forced to not only practice, but reflect on the material, I found that I once again gained the ability to truly absorb and retain information.</p>

<p>I may not be a fan of putting my thought process into words, but if doing so will help me improve as a developer and a person, I&rsquo;m all for it. <strong>That&rsquo;s</strong> why I&rsquo;m writing this post right now. <strong>That&rsquo;s</strong> why I&rsquo;m headed to DBC. I can&rsquo;t wait for week 2.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The teacher becomes the student]]></title>
    <link href="http://andrewada.ms/blog/2014/the-teacher-becomes-the-student/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-22T12:28:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://andrewada.ms/blog/2014/the-teacher-becomes-the-student</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past several months, I have been learning how to code. For some reason, I had always been intimidated by code, and had turned down many opportunities to learn. I had convinced myself that I needed to focus on teaching and music, rather than accept the fact that I was afraid to fail. However, as soon as I took the leap, I was hooked.</p>

<p>At the onset, I adopted the attitude that I would &ldquo;teach myself&rdquo;, and simply absorb new information as I went along. After all, that&rsquo;s how it worked when I was a kid &ndash; building silly websites and copying javascript examples! While this was possible to an extent, I soon discovered that I couldn&rsquo;t do everything alone. The number of people online who are eager to share their knowledge about any given subject is unbelievable. I needed to become a student and allow myself to learn from them.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>After completing a few tracks on <a title="Code Academy" href="http://codeacademy.com" target="_blank">Code Academy</a>, I enrolled in <a title="Udacity CS 101" href="https://www.udacity.com/course/cs101" target="_blank">CS101 on Udacity.</a> From there, I moved on to <a title="Udacity CS 253" href="https://www.udacity.com/course/cs253" target="_blank">Steve Huffman&rsquo;s web development course</a>, and even took a refresher in <a title="Udacity ST 101" href="https://www.udacity.com/course/st101" target="_blank">statistics</a>. In just over a month, I was parsing HTML, managing databases, and using tons of cool acronyms. I&rsquo;ve have since been working on numerous code challenges and side projects, and diving into too many books to remember.</p>

<p>When I first read about <a title="Dev Bootcamp" href="http://devbootcamp.com/" target="_blank">Dev Bootcamp</a>, it seemed like exactly the type of experience I needed: intense learning, constant collaboration and support, and the prospect of a new career in the field I was engrossed in.  After reading overwhelmingly positive reviews from alumni (like <a title="Natasha the Robot" href="http://natashatherobot.com/" target="_blank">Natasha the Robot</a>), I decided to take a chance and apply.</p>

<p>Now I&rsquo;m in! In June, I&rsquo;ll be leaving my friends, family, and job in Kansas City to move to Chicago for 9 weeks. I still have no idea if I&rsquo;ll stay, move back, or head somewhere else entirely, but this is a huge step. I&rsquo;ve already begun the transition from Python to Ruby, and am following <a title="DBC Prep Objectives" href="https://gist.github.com/andrewjadams3/9572050#dbc-prep-objectives" target="_blank">this checklist</a> to prepare. I&rsquo;ll be updating this blog (with considerably shorter posts from now on) with projects, discoveries, failures, and successes. I can&rsquo;t wait to find out where these next few months will lead!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
